A Guide to the Massanutten Hatchery Photographs, 1934-1948: SC 0300
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Massanutten Hatchery Photographs,
1934-1948
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Massanutten Hatchery
SC 0300
.2 cubic feet; 1 box
The Massanutten Hatchery Photographs, 1934-1948, comprise black-and-white photographs of chickens likely used for the hatchery's promotional materials and sales catalogs. Photographs of the Massanutten Hatchery interior and exterior and the hatchery's breeding farm in McGaheysville are also included.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Tim Abbott Americana in November 2019.
Administrative History
Massanutten Hatchery, Inc., variously known as Massanutten Farms Hatchery, was formed in 1923 by C. B. Williamson (1880-1958), former superintendent of the Chesapeake Western Railway, and Gilbert Spitzer (1886-1935). The chicken hatchery was located at 1020 S. Main Street in Harrisonburg. The hatchery also operated a breeding farm in McGaheysville, Virginia.
With a capacity of more than 200,000 chicks, Massanutten Hatchery was widely recognized as the largest commercial hatchery in the south. They specialized in White Leghorns, Rhode Island Reds, New Hampshire Reds, and Barred Rocks. At some point, the hatchery transitioned to include turkeys.
In 1953, Harold W. Clark, a Pennsylvania businessman with experience in poultry husbandry, purchased the hatchery from C. B. Williamson and Bessie Baker, Gilbert Spitzer's widow. Charles W. Wampler (1885-1976) became president of the hatchery in 1956. Massanutten Hatchery, Inc. is last listed in the 1970 Harrisonburg city directory. At that time, Charles W. Wampler was listed as its president, Marion I. Eberly as its vice president, and William D. Wampler as its secretary/treasurer.
During the 1970s, James Madison University acquired the hatchery building and renovated it into an experimental theatre space - Wampler Experimental Theatre/Wampler Building. The building was also known as Theatre II and housed JMU's School of Theatre and Dance administrative and faculty offices and classrooms.
The hatchery building was razed in the summer of 2010. As of 2020, a JMU parking lot (K Lot), a FedEx Office, and JMU Print Services occupy the former approximate location of Massanutten Hatchery.
Scope and Content
The Massanutten Hatchery Photographs, 1934-1948, comprise black-and-white photographs of chickens likely used for the hatchery's promotional materials and sales catalogs. Photographs of the Massanutten Hatchery interior and exterior and the hatchery's breeding farm in McGaheysville are also included.
The photographs document the breeds of chickens (and chicks) available through the hatchery, specifically White Leghorns, Barred Rocks, and New Hampshire Reds and/or Rhode Island Reds. Over the course of its business, the hatchery had both variety of Reds available. As the photographs are all black-and-white, it is difficult to determine which breed of Red is documented in each particular photograph. The chickens are photographed in their flocks, at the breeding farm in McGaheysville, in the hatchery in Harrisonburg, and in posed photographs usually featuring only one chicken in profile. Interior shots of the hatchery primarily document chickens, but a selection include workers and equipment. Photographs of the hatchery's exterior are included.
Many of the photographs include captions, notations, or specifications for cropping or other edits to be made for publication. Photographers, as identified by stamps on the back of photographs, include Lee Studio (Harrisonburg), Dean-Kaylor Studio (Harrisonburg), and Gitchell's Studio (Harrisonburg).
Four catalogs document the hatchery's marketing and sales techniques and include comparable photographs to the originals found in the collection.
Arrangement
The photographs were received in no particular order. The photographs of chickens are mostly arranged according to breed and style of photograph. No attempt was made by the archivist to distinguish between photographs of New Hampshire Reds and Rhode Island Reds. All photographs documenting what appears to be a red variety of chicken are grouped together. The collection is further arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Aerial photographs of Massanutten Hatchery, Hoyle Garber Collection, Mt. Jackson Museum.
Harrisonburg Historic Map Collection 1873-1982 (bulk 1903-1956), SC 0050, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va.
Bibliography
Harrisonburg Chamber of Commerce. Harrisonburg, Virginia: A General Industrial Survey. Harrisonburg, VA: The Garrison Press, 1926.
Laura Cochran and Lindsay Marti, "Enrollment levels after four year rise," The Breeze, November 5, 2001.
Amber Logsdon, "With new Home Comes Reflections On Past Performance Spaces," The Breeze, April 22, 2010.
"New Firm Takes Over Hatchery," Daily News-Record, July 20, 1953.
Obituary for Gilbert R. Spitzer, Daily News-Record, August 1, 1935.
Obituary for C. B. Williamson, Daily News-Record, February 5, 1958.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Chickens -- Hatcheries -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Poultry -- Hatcheries -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Poultry -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Poultry industry -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg; Agriculture -- Economic aspects; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Photographs; Negatives (photographs); Sales catalogs
- Massanutten Hatchery catalogs, 1934-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chicks, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Barred Rocks (in profile), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Barred Rocks (flocks), 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- New Hampshire Reds/Rhode Island Reds (in profile), 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- New Hampshire Reds/Rhode Island Reds (flocks), 1935-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- White Leghorns (in profile), 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- White Leghorns (flocks), 1935-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Massanutten Hatchery interior and exterior, 1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 9, Mapcase 1, Drawer 5, Folder 1)
- Negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photograph clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)